Brutal summer. That's how the global
economy is setting up according to the
latest incoming data. Manufacturing,
it's up right now, but the faster it
goes today, the worse it's going to be
in a couple months time. Services, the
vast majority of the economy, they're
already getting hit and in some places
like Europe, getting crushed. The
Europeans just set a 62-month
low. If you've been paying attention to
anything other than the mainstream
narrative, you'll already recognize how
this is a very similar setup to last
summer, which fed right into job losses,
contracting incomes,
and rising unemployment.
It also fed right into the Fed's rate
cutting, just to toss that one in there,
too. While officials were focused on
inflation for the second straight year,
for the second straight summer, it was
job problems which brought out the
Pringles can. In fact, that's just what
S&P Global said with the release of
purchasing managers indexes around the
world. For the US specifically, quote,
"The overall flat picture represents the
worst back-to-back months for employment
since late 2024. Manufacturing head
counts fell for the first time in 9
months, and only a marginal return to
jobs growth was reported in the services
sector, which will disappear as we'll
see. As companies reported concerns over
the need to reduce staffing costs in the
face of the uncertain demand environment
and high input prices. So, consumers are
being forced to choose, and they're
choosing to give up on some
discretionary services already,
especially over there in beleaguered
Europe. Manufacturing, running fast for
the time being, but the faster it goes
today, the worse it will be in a couple
months.
And once this latest artificial
distortion high subsides, that combined
with, you know, more job losses,
contracting income, rising unemployment,
and on and on the list goes, it really
does set us up for a brutal summer. Or
over in Europe, maybe even a brutal
spring, especially where it comes to
services. So, we'll go over what's going
on with services as well as why
manufacturing going well today is a
recipe for trouble tomorrow heading into
that summertime.
So, starting with the US, S&P Global put
out a rebound in its April PMIs after
the what was really alarming drop for
them in March. But, it's not a rebound
though. It's a It's a combination of
artificiality and short-run fluctuation
starting with much higher prices. In
other words, the increase in the
headline numbers represent more trouble
and problems than positives.
Manufacturing is the perfect example.
That index jumped to 54.0 from 52.3
reaching the highest level in 4 years.
So, you'd think that would be great news
right off the bat, especially for
industry which has been struggling badly
and forgot how to grow all this time.
But, this is yet another example of
front-loading. And even worse in the
short run than what we saw to begin 2025
with tariffs. As SPG itself put it,
quote, "The manufacturing sector saw
output rise at the sharpest rate for 4
years fueled by the largest influx of
new orders since May of 2022." Sounds
really good. However, both output and
new orders growth were boosted by client
stock building amid concerns over supply
availability and price hikes due to the
ongoing war. The rise in orders was
driven by domestic demand as export
sales of goods fell at an increased
rate. So, it's not a jump in actual
organic demand. It's instead everyone
rushing to buy and build before costs go
up even further or shortages of material
materialize through the closure of
Hormuz and the lack of supply chain
flexibility for a lot more than just
petroleum as we've been talking about.
Oil feeds into food via fertilizer, but
also think about plastics. Plastic is in
everything, even if it's just packaging.
Well, the amount of oil currently being
choked off at you know, historic levels,
there is a very high and growing chance
the world sees shortages in a matter of
weeks, not years, not months, but weeks.
And thus, that gives us the next part of
what SPG had to say, quote, "In addition
to shipping related disruptions due to
the war, shortages were also linked to
the additional purchasing of safety
stocks. Purchasing activity rose at the
second fastest rate seen for nearly 4
years, surpassed only by the jump in
buying activity seen shortly after last
spring's tariff announcements.
Artificial high meets another artificial
high."
So, with everyone rushing to front-load
orders and purchasing, we are going to
see, just like last year, we're going to
see another bout of payback over the
months ahead, which means big trouble
because as I already told you in the
intro, manufacturing firms are already
cutting back on jobs due to higher input
costs. In other words, they are not
hiring more people to handle the
short-run increase in the workload
because they know it's only going to be
short-run. Once the safety orders run
dry,
that's it. Not only are producers
expecting higher costs to linger, they
also know the revenues are going to
disappear, too, which is why the PMI can
hit a 4-year high, yet manufacturers are
already cutting employment anyway. As
SPG said, we saw this just last year,
and it led directly to the job losses
which showed up more obviously by the
time we got to summer. And then, let's
not forget all the negative implications
that went along with flatter beverage.
After all, it was the payroll reports,
the negative payroll reports, which
began to really expose the cockroaches
in private credit. So, an even weaker
labor market this summer moving forward
is just going to keep up the pressure on
the macroeconomy and everything else
downstream of it.
What is a Eurodollar University
membership? It's where understanding the
monetary world isn't a mystery, it's a
method. If you're serious about your
financial education and you want clarity
in a world of volatility and
misunderstanding,
this is for you.
Mainstream education has left so many
gaps on the most foundational concepts,
making sense of everything is
practically impossible otherwise. With
our memberships, we'll fill in
everything that you've been missing.
Whether you're starting out or
sharpening your edge, our membership
scale with your goals. At Euro Dollar
University, we teach you about how money
really works so that you can evaluate
fundamentals and make grounded
decisions. With a Euro Dollar University
membership, you get a comprehensive
library of foundational and advanced
lectures, in-depth case studies, and
real-world analyses, live Q&A sessions,
regular updates on macro trends, and
even some central bank policies. And
most important, how to interpret
critical derivative market signals you
will not find anywhere else.
You can't be in position to succeed if
you don't know how it all really works
and fits together. So, if you're ready
to explore, master monetary systems both
past and future with structure, clarity,
and confidence, click the link in the
description to visit
eurodollar.university/memberships
to join us today.
So, for what sounds like good news, it's
just going to be looming payback on the
manufacturing side of the economy. The
higher it goes, the faster it gets there
in the near term, the worse it's going
to be over the months ahead, the bigger
the payback, the more trouble by
summertime.
So, the higher the PMI goes, it really
is a bad sign for summer. But, as
difficult as that will be for
production, the vastly larger
non-manufacturing contingent is already
struggling, too. For SPG and their
numbers, their US services PMI March had
shockingly dropped below 50, the first
contraction in several years, but here
in April it did rebound if only to 51.3.
But the rebound means nothing. As you
can see here, that's what these things
do on a month-to-month basis. They're
down, then they go up, then they're down
again. What really matters is the trend.
It's almost like the stock market and
following individual stocks, is that
trend hitting lower lows or is it going
the other way and reaching higher highs?
For SPG's services PMI in April, it's
coming off that lower low and by only
bouncing minimally, it tells you the
downtrend is still there even before we
dig into the details.
But those details, they leave no doubt
about what's going on with services
providers. Let's go back to S&P Global.
Average prices charged for goods and
services rose in April the fastest rate
since July 2022
amid increases in input prices and
supply scarcities. While manufacturers
reported an especially steep jump in
goods prices with the rate of inflation
at a 10-month high, service sector
selling price inflation also accelerated
to reach a 45-month high. So costs went
way up for all the non-economic
distortions and they did so amidst
questionable, to put it kindly, demand.
Everyone keeps using the term
uncertainty, it's really just plain
weakness. Pulling back. They They can
blame uncertainty, but it's just basic
economics and perfectly consistent with
an energy shock of this magnitude. So
costs are going way up at the same time
we get this, quote, "Service sector
activity remained especially subdued.
Although recovering slightly from
March's dip, the rate of expansion was
the second weakest in the past year due
to a further cooling off of demand
growth. New business placed at service
providers rose only marginally, which
means it was basically flat, and at the
slowest rate seen in over the past 2
years led by an ongoing decline in
exports. Lost sales were commonly linked
by survey contributors to the
uncertainty disruption caused by the war
in the Middle East, alongside other
government policies and vastly more
important than either, affordability
issue. So, translation, yeah,
affordability, which just means the weak
economy prior to the Iran conflict, just
got a whole bunch weaker as higher
energy prices are going to force
consumers and businesses to choose to
pull back in areas which they can,
and they start with service providers.
Now, we've already seen consumers, for
example, I mean, sentiment is down
sharply. Surveys showing a strong
likelihood of them skipping vacations,
again, brutal summer, dining out less,
fewer leisure activities, that kind of
thing. But, it's also cutting back on
service subscriptions, too, being forced
into hard choices because without income
growth, and incomes, as I pointed out
already, already contracting long before
we got to March, higher gasoline is just
a is just a killer. And the longer it
goes on, the more economic killing it's
going to do beyond what we've already
seen here, and out of the data so far
collected and released around the rest
of the economy. This is just the tip of
the iceberg. Flat beverage plus energy
shock really does equal summertime
trouble. And you know what we said about
the past couple of summers. The Fed
knows, the Fed really knows, because
after all, when did the rate cuts
happen? At the tail end of the prior two
summers. Summertime is the time for
economic trouble to really show up.
Now, as bad as it is looking on this
side of the Atlantic, the fallout from
energy shock is registering even harder
and more clearly over in Europe. Now,
yesterday, I went over the crashing
commercial sentiment from the zoo, the
quote free fall in consumer confidence,
again, using European Commission's own
words there, plus unemployment that
jumped across Scandinavia and job losses
returning to the UK, though, in reality,
they weren't really returning. Flat
beverage never really actually went
anywhere in Britain. Today, same
negatives in the PMIs as seen in the US,
just amplified and more negative. A lot
more negative. First of all, European
services
dropped to 47.4,
down from just 50.2 in March. And 50.2
not all that good, but 47.4 was the
lowest in, get this, 62
months. And because of that crash in
services, the overall composite index
for Europe dropped to 48.6,
the first decline there in a year and a
half. So, Europe was supposed to be
recovering, though it never really was,
we know that. But at the very least,
there were some positive numbers. But
now with the energy shock shaping up
more and more like previous historical
experience, contraction, real
contraction, looms everywhere, and I
mean everywhere as we head towards
summer. To S&P Global we go, quote, "The
decline in output at the start of the
second quarter was centered on the
services sector, no surprise. Here,
business activity decreased for the
first time in almost a year, and at the
s- deepest pace since February 2021."
Remember February 2021? Yeah. "New
orders decreased in the Eurozone for the
second consecutive month in April, and
at the fastest pace for almost a year
and a half. As was the case with output,
the overall reduction was driven by
falling services new business. And
services optimism, sentiment here, was
the weakest in 3 and 1/2 years, while in
the manufacturing sector confidence
dropped to a 17-month low. So, another
survey suggesting services and
confidence and sentiment is crashing."
Now, just like the US, manufacturing in
Europe did pick up, rising to 52.2 for
the Eurozone, which was its highest
level in nearly four years, which kind
of just goes to show just how pitiful
the forgot how to grow goods economies
been in Europe last couple of years
when, you know, 52.2 is a 47-month high.
Even so, same thing. It's due to an
upsurge in orders, buying, the frenzied
activity that's associated with
artificial distortion, same as before
tariffs last year. As SPG said, quote,
"Manufacturing new orders, on the other
hand, increased at the fastest pace in 4
years, supported by a first rise in new
export business, which includes
intra-eurozone trade, since February of
2022." But then only saying some of that
was due to emergency stocking. If we're
being honest, the entire increase is
about distortion, pulling forward
demand, to be prices. They keep
referring to scarcity and get ahead of
supply chain problems and material
shortages.
These are not the ingredients for a
recovery or sustained advance. Even
SPG's chief economist, he had to admit,
quote, "The sustained growth of
manufacturing, meanwhile, seen in April,
comes with something of a sting in the
tail, as demand for goods is being
buoyed by stock building as companies
scramble to secure purchases ahead of
further price hikes or supply
shortages." Manufacturers have increased
their buying of inputs to a degree not
witnessed since early 2022
as supply chain delays have also risen
to the most widespread since the
pandemic. Again, these are not
ingredients for a sustainable advance.
It's a fake manufacturing surge that's
going on worldwide and one that is
already creating a huge hole in the
near-term future after the upturn dies
down, which it will. Payback for a
second straight year in manufacturing,
combined with a pressured falloff in
services, leaving summertime exposed,
really exposed, to all of the above
negatives.
But given all that, maybe the best
example of this this divergence in
manufacturing and how positivity in the
near-term is actually negativity, bigger
negativity, a couple months down the
road, that comes from Japan. Where
Japanese numbers, some of the details
got to be extreme, really even greater
extremes on the upside. Yet, Japanese
sentiment was even more extreme on the
downside because the Japanese know the
more that they have to do today, the
less there's going to be for them in the
summertime.
Now, the overall index for manufacturing
in Japan jumped to 54.9,
which is the highest since January 2022.
So, again, already the same pattern.
But, the production or output index
soared to its highest rate since, get
this,
February 2014,
showing you just how much of a rush
there is and at least in that part of
Asia to get everything done as quickly
as possible. This is not healthy. And we
know it's not because those Japanese
producers who responded to this S&P
Global, they're now the most pessimistic
they've been since 2020. Quote, "In
fact, business confidence fell to the
lowest level since August of 2020 amidst
the depths of the COVID-19 pandemic. The
war in the Middle East was a key factor
dampening optimism. Thank you, Captain
Obvious. With the current strong
manufacturing performance unlikely to be
sustained unless uncertainties reduced
and supply chains stabilize." So, for
Japanese services, we also get the same
story to the US and Europe. Though,
nowhere near as extreme as Europe. I
think I don't think anything is is
extreme as Europe right now. Services
outlooks are down. Activity is only
slowing slightly at the moment in Japan,
but the trajectory has the Japanese
economy right in line and right on track
for a summertime showdown and slowdown
at the very best. All the while, the
Bank of Japan, though, as we know,
probably going to be raising its policy
rate or at the very least continue to
talk about doing the same thing. Same
for Europe, by the way. There is a
non-trivial chance the ECB undertakes a
rate hike by the start of the summer,
though. It looks like maybe policymakers
will be able to hold back on themselves
at their meeting next week. Maybe.
But, the hawks, you just you know the
hawks, they're just itching to raise
rates and make the same mistake that
Jean-Claude Trichet did 18 years ago.
And when did Trichet raise rates for the
ECB? It was the early summer of 2008,
just as the wheels were starting to
really fall off, focused as policy
makers always are on oil prices rather
than the vastly more relevant energy
shock that comes along from them.
So, services globally already being
dragged down or just about to be on the
cusp of the cliff, ready to join Europe
in its beleaguered 62-month low, already
on the wrong side of the edge.
This isn't some mystery or riddle. Not
only do we have prior historical
examples, which all uniformly show how
energy shocks force consumers and
businesses to have to sacrifice
spending, and for employers to have to
cut back on employment. Services are
just right at the front of the line for
both of those. It's also just plain
common sense, basic small economics.
There's no inflation for many of this,
apart from the short-run contribution of
energy prices to near-term CPIs, but all
that really represents is how much pain
those prices will inflict on a global
economy that already cannot afford price
increases from 5 years ago, let alone
another big, stinging, painful rise in
energy. So, with services already
displaying signs of distress and worse
in some places, then you add back the
payback that's looming in the
manufacturing side, and it is all
scheduled to recombine over the next
couple months into what looks to be
another brutal summer, another more
brutal summer filled with flat beverage
and Pringles.
And yes, Europe is definitely leading
the charge in that direction.
Free-falling consumer confidence,
crashing commercial sentiment, rising
unemployment, and all the details in the
video link below. As always, thank you
very much for joining me. Huge thank you
Euro dollar University members and
subscribers and until next time,
take care.